[{"question":"One group of neurotransmitter receptors is the following statements about metabotropic receptors is false?  the metabotropic receptors. Which one of","a":"Both muscanaric and B-adrenergic receptors are metabotropic receptors","b":"Metabotropic receptors are coupled with A proteins","c":"Metabotropic receptors can stimulate gene  expression.","d":"Muscanaric receptors bind with acetylcholine","hint":"","correct":"b"},{"question":"Which of the following statements is correct?","a":"The internal ear receives sound waves and  directs them to the ear drum","b":"The membranous canals are suspended in  the endolymph of the bony canals.","c":"The ear ossicles increase the efficiency of transmission of sound waves to the inner  ear.","d":"The malleus is attached to the oval window and the stapes is attached to the temporal membrane of the cochlea.","hint":"","correct":"c"},{"question":"Which of the following terms is not correctly  matched with its feature?","a":"Efferent neurons - Carries signals from CNS  to the effector.","b":"Axon terminal - Possess neurotransmitter  containing vesicle.","c":"Limbic system Along with the hypothalamus, it is involved in the regulation of sexual behaviour, expression of emotional reactions and motivation.","d":"Association areas - Present in cerebellum and responsible for functions like intersensory associations, memory and communication.","hint":"","correct":"d"},{"question":"Which of the following statement is incorrect?","a":"The ear ossicle attached to tympanic membrane is malleus","b":"Opsin (of rhodopsin) develops from vitamin A.","c":"The pressure on ear drum is equalised by  Eustachian tube","d":"Otolith organ consists of saccule and utricle.","hint":"","correct":"b"},{"question":"Trochlear nerve supplies:","a":"Nasal epithelium","b":"Superior oblique eye muscles","c":"Inferior oblique eye muscle","d":"Superior rectus eye muscle","hint":"","correct":"d"},{"question":"An axon has four terminal ends connected with dendrites of four different neurons. Its nerve impulse will","a":"Become weak due to distribution into four.","b":"Travel in all the four neurons with equal  strength","c":"Pass on to one neuron only","d":"Travel to none because the movement of impulse is from dendrite to axon","hint":"","correct":"b"},{"question":"Receptors which are sensitive to pain are known  as:","a":"Rheoreceptor","b":"Algesireceptors","c":"Tangoreceptors","d":"Mechanoreceptors","hint":"","correct":"b"},{"question":"A circular canal which is found in limbus part of eyes is called","a":"Hyaloid canal","b":"Canal of Schlemm","c":"Canal of Cloquet","d":"Eustachian tube","hint":"","correct":"b"},{"question":"An example of autonomous nervous system is:","a":"Swallowing food","b":"Pupillary reflex","c":"Peristalsis of intestine","d":"Knee-jerk response","hint":"","correct":"c"},{"question":"The eyes of tigers and wolves shine (reflect back the light focused on them) because:","a":"cornea is opaque","b":"retina does not have enough rods","c":"retina has only rods and no cones","d":"None of the above","hint":"","correct":"d"},{"question":"Our ear can hear the frequency of sound waves","a":"20 to 20,000 cycles/sec","b":"1000 to 2000 cycles/sec","c":"5000 to 7000 cycles/sec","d":"5000 to 10,000 cycles/sec","hint":"","correct":"a"},{"question":"In the blind spot, where the optic nerves leave  the eye:","a":"Rods and cones are absent","b":"Only cones are present","c":"Only rods are present","d":"Special neurons are present","hint":"","correct":"a"},{"question":"Part of brain responsible for hearing is:","a":"Cerebellum","b":"Cerebrum","c":"Medulla","d":"Hypothalamus","hint":"","correct":"b"},{"question":"Fenestra ovalis is the opening of:","a":"Cranium","b":"Tympanum","c":"Tympanic cavity","d":"Brain","hint":"","correct":"c"},{"question":"Which is not a reflex action?","a":"Swallowing of food","b":"Shivering in cold","c":"Salivation at choicest food","d":"Closure of eyelid by flashing light","hint":"","correct":"b"},{"question":"No image formation occurs  retina because:on blind-spot of","a":"It is not present on the optical axis of the eye.","b":"Here cones and rods are absent.","c":"On this part only cones are present.","d":"The nerve fibres of this region do not  contribute in the formation of optic chiasma","hint":"","correct":"b"},{"question":"Center for sense of smell is:","a":"Cerebellum","b":"Olfactory lobes","c":"Cerebrum","d":"Midbrain","hint":"","correct":"c"},{"question":"Route of reflex arc is:","a":"Receptors, effectors, grey mater and motor  fibres","b":"Receptors, sensory fibres, grey mater, motor fibres and effectors","c":"Sensory fibres, grey mater, motor-fibres, receptors and effectors","d":"Effectors, grey mater, motor, sensory fibres and receptors","hint":"","correct":"b"},{"question":"The small canal leading from pinna into the  head in mammals is:","a":"Haversian canal","b":"Ext. auditory meatus","c":"Inguinal canal","d":"Eustachian tube","hint":"","correct":"b"},{"question":"Ear drum is known as:","a":"Tympanic membrane","b":"Tensor tympani","c":"Scala tympani","d":"Scala vestibuli","hint":"","correct":"a"},{"question":"The nodes of Ranvier are:","a":"the points in which the axons is exposed.","b":"the contact points found over the non-  myelinated nerve fibre.","c":"areas in which the axons swell up","d":"areas where the neurilemma touches the  axon.","hint":"","correct":"a"},{"question":"Which of the following statement is correct?","a":"Electrical synapses are more common in  our neural system than chemical synapses.","b":"The new potential in post-synaptic neuron  may be either excitatory or inhibitory","c":"Hypothalamus is the major coordination  centre for sensory and motor signaling.","d":"The tracts of nerve fibres that connect two cerebral hemispheres are called corpora bigemina.","hint":"","correct":"b"},{"question":"\"Jumping of the action potential\" at the nodes  of Ranvier is known as:","a":"Saltatory conduction","b":"Neurotransmission","c":"Recovery phase","d":"Active phase","hint":"","correct":"a"},{"question":"The rods and cones of the eye retinal layer are modified:","a":"Hair","b":"Unipolar neurons","c":"Bipolar neurons","d":"Multipolar neurons","hint":"","correct":"c"},{"question":"Which of the following statement is correct  ?","a":"The space within cochlea called scala  media is filled with endolymph.","b":"The vestibular apparatus is composed of two semi-circular canals and the otolith organ consisting of the saccule and utricle.","c":"The external auditory meatus helps in equalising the pressures on either sides of  the ear drum.","d":"The membranes constituting cochlea, the Reissner's and basilar, divide the surrounding perilymph filled bony labyrinth into an upper scala tympani and a lower scala vestibuli.","hint":"","correct":"a"},{"question":"When a physician elicits the knee-jerk reflex by tapping deep tendons in the knee, the normal response is for the lower leg to swing forward. When this happens:","a":"muscles in the back of the lower leg are  contracting but that in the front are relaxing","b":"muscles in the front of the lower leg are  contracting but that in the back are relaxing.","c":"muscles in the back of the thigh are  contracting but that in the front are relaxing.","d":"muscles in the front of the thigh are  contracting but that in the back are relaxing.","hint":"","correct":"d"},{"question":"Which of these is an example of conditioned  reflex?","a":"Watering of mouth at the taste of food","b":"Withdrawal of hand on touching a hot plate.","c":"Cycling","d":"Flowing of tears while peeling and cutting  onions","hint":"","correct":"c"},{"question":"In snakes, eye lids are:","a":"Immovable","b":"Movable","c":"Absent","d":"All of these","hint":"","correct":"c"},{"question":"In mammalian eye, the power of accommodation is due to:","a":"Regulating light through iris","b":"Focussing by cornea","c":"Changing the focal length of eye lens by ciliary body","d":"Changing the diameter of pupil","hint":"","correct":"c"},{"question":"The autonomic nervous system has control over:","a":"Reflex action","b":"Sense organs","c":"Internal organs","d":"Skeletal muscles","hint":"","correct":"c"},{"question":"Nerve impulses are initiated by nerve fibres only when the membrane shall become more permeable to:","a":"Adrenaline","b":"Phosphorus","c":"Sodium ions","d":"Potassium ions","hint":"","correct":"c"},{"question":"The parts of the neurons that perform basic cellular  functions such as protein synthesis are the:","a":"Axons","b":"Dendrites","c":"Synaptic knobs","d":"Soma","hint":"","correct":"d"},{"question":"Which of the following correctly traces the  energy of sound waves into the ear?","a":"Auditory canal-eardrum-ear bones-cochlea","b":"Eardrum-auditory canal-cochlea-ear bones","c":"Auditory canal-ear bones-eardrum-cochlea","d":"Eardrum-auditory canal-ear bones-cochlea","hint":"","correct":"a"},{"question":"The sense of balance is maintained with the  help of:","a":"Hammer","b":"Stirrup ","c":"Semicircular canals","d":"Cochlea","hint":"","correct":"c"},{"question":"The enzyme required for the conduction of  nerve impulse across synapse is:","a":"Peroxidase","b":"Choline acetylase","c":"Ascorbic acid oxidase","d":"Succinic dehydrogenase","hint":"","correct":"b"},{"question":"Which is activated in stress condition?","a":"Somatic","b":"Sympathetic","c":"Parasympathetic","d":"Whole ANS","hint":"","correct":"b"},{"question":"Ear is most sensitive to sound waves of:","a":"1000 cycles/sec","b":"10000 cycles/sec","c":"6000 cycles/sec","d":"20 cycles/sec","hint":"","correct":"a"},{"question":"The pinna of the ear is composed of:","a":"Elastic cartilage","b":"Hyaline cartilage","c":"White fibrocartilage","d":"Bone","hint":"","correct":"a"},{"question":"Vermis is a part of: ","a":"Optic lobe","b":"Midbrain","c":"Cerebellum","d":"Medulla oblongata","hint":"","correct":"c"},{"question":"An abnormal production of antidiuretic hormone (ADH) could result from a dysfunction of:","a":"Hypothalamus","b":"Choroid plexus","c":"Medulla oblongata","d":"Reticular activation system","hint":"","correct":"a"}]